A Finding Aid to the Raymond Saroff papers, 1953-2009, in the Archives of American Art
Archives of American Art
Raymond Saroff papers
1953-2009
Archives of American Art
Saroff, Raymond
AAA.saroraym
Archival Resource Key
1.2 Linear feet
The Raymond Saroff papers are dated 1953-2009 and comprise 1.2 linear feet. Letters, printed material and photographs compiled by Saroff document his interest in Claes Oldenburg and "Happenings." Also included are a videotape of Saroff's film Claes Oldenburg's "Ray Gun Theater – 1962" and receipts for artwork purchased for his modern art collection. The 2014 addition includes a catalog essay by curator and collector Howard Rose, Saroff's partner, for an exhibition of their folk art collection at Bard College (1991). Also found are financial records regarding his collections, related printed material, and photographs of artwork.
Provenance
Gift of Raymond Saroff, 2011 and 2014.
Restrictions on Access
Use of original material requires an appointment and is limited to the Archives' Washington, D.C. Research Center. Use of archival audiovisual recordings with no duplicate access copy requires advance notice.
Biographical Note
Raymond Saroff (b. 1922), a resident of New York City, is a filmmaker and collector of both modern and folk art. Saroff pursued his interest in American folk art with his partner, Howard Rose, a scholar and art collector. In 1960, Saroff purchased Leg, a paper maché sculpture by Claes Oldenburg. Around the same time, he became interested in "Happenings." Using borrowed equipment, Saroff filmed a series of 1962 "Happenings" known as "Ray Gun Theater" that Oldenburg presented to small audiences in a storefront on East Second Street, New York City.
Scope and Content Note
The Raymond Saroff papers are dated 1953-2009 and comprise 1.2 linear feet. Letters, printed material and photographs compiled by Saroff document his interest in Claes Oldenburg and "Happenings." Also included are a videotape of Saroff's film Claes Oldenburg's "Ray Gun Theater – 1962" and receipts for artwork purchased for his modern art collection. The 2014 addition includes a catalog essay by curator and collector Howard Rose, Saroff's partner, for an exhibition of their folk art collection at Bard College (1991). Also found are financial records regarding his collections, related printed material, and photographs of artwork.
Arrangement
The collection is arranged in 2 series:
Series 1: Raymond Saroff papers concerning Claes Oldenburg, 1953-2009 (Box 1; 0.5 linear feet)
Series 2: Addition to the Raymond Saroff papers, 1960-2009 (Boxes 1-2; 0.7 linear feet)
Photographs; Video recordings; Collectors and collecting -- New York (State) -- New York; Oldenburg, Claes, 1929-
- Raymond Saroff papers concerning Claes Oldenburg, 1953-2009; Series 1; Archival Resource Key; 0.5 Linear feet Box 1
  Scope and Contents
  This series documents Saroff's interest in Claes Oldenburg. Of note is Saroff's film Claes Oldenburg's Ray Gun Theater - 1962". In 1962, ten "Happenings" conceived by Oldenburg known as "Ray Gun Theater" were presented in New York City at a store on East Second Street. Each evening-long event was filmed by Saroff, who then edited the film to approximately two hours before releasing it commercially. Correspondence concerns gifts and loans from Saroff's art collection. Financial records consist of sales receipts including one for his purchase of Leg. Printed material includes exhibition catalogs, clippings, and miscellaneous items. Photographs and a transparency are of Oldenburg's work in several media.
  - Letters, 1969-2009; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Financial Records - Sales Receipts (A-Z by Gallery), 1953-1985; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Claes Oldenburg's "Ray Gun Theater - 1962" by Raymond Saroff (1962), 1995; Archival Resource Key; 1 Videocassettes (VHS) (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Printed Material, Archival Resource Key (Box 1)
    - Exhibition Catalogs, circa 1960-1995; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 4-7)
    - Clippings, 1960-1995; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - Press Kit, 1995; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - Miscellaneous Items, 1964-1995; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Photographs of Artwork by Oldenburg, 1960s-1970s; Archival Resource Key; includes 1 color transparency (Box 1, Folder 11)
- Addition to the Raymond Saroff papers, 1960-2009; Series 2; Archival Resource Key; 0.7 Linear feet Boxes 1-2
  Correspondence pertains to sales and loans from Saroff's Oldenburg art collection as well as from the folk art collection developed and owned by Saroff and Howard Rose. Among the writings are Rose's published and unpublished manuscripts on American folk art. Financial records include a collection inventory with provenance, attribution, and price information. Also found are receipts from galleries and auction houses documenting loans and sales. Printed material includes clippings, exhibition announcements and catalogs. Photographs are of artwork.
  - Correspondence about Claes Oldenburg Collection, 1983-1985; 1962; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Correspondence about Sales and Loans, 1989-1995; 1962; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Writings by Howard Rose on American Folk Art, 1982-1990; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Inventories of the Saroff and Rose Folk Art Collection, 1983-1995; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Financial Records - Receipts for Sales, Deliveries, Consignments, 1984-1995; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Printed Material, Archival Resource Key (Box 1)
    - Clippings, 1988-1992; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 17)
    - Announcements, Invitations and Press Releases, 1963-1999; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 18)
    - Exhibition Catalogs, 1965-1995; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 19)
    - Film Catalogs, 1963-1988; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 20)
    - Film Catalogs, 1963-1988; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 1)
    - Periodical, 1967; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Photographs of Artwork, circa 1960-2000; Archival Resource Key; includes slides and color transparencies (Box 2, Folder 3)